{
  "title": "Theory_of_Computation - Regular_Language — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Regular_Language — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(\\Sigma = \\{a, b, c\\} \\). For \\(x \\in \\Sigma^* \\), and \\(\\alpha \\in \\Sigma \\), let \\(\\# _\\alpha (x) \\) denote the number of occurrences of \\(\\alpha \\) in \\(x \\).  <br><br>\nWhich one or more of the following option(s) define(s) regular language(s)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{ a^m b^n \\mid m, n \\geq 0 \\} \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{ a, b \\}^* \\cap \\{ a^m b^n c^{m-n} \\mid m \\geq n \\geq 0 \\} \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{ w \\mid w \\in \\{ a, b \\}^*, \\#_a(w) \\equiv 2 \\ (\\text{mod}\\ 7), \\#_b(w) \\equiv 3 \\ (\\text{mod}\\ 9) \\} \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{ w \\mid w \\in \\{ a, b \\}^*, \\#_a(w) \\equiv 2 \\ (\\text{mod}\\ 7), \\#_a(w) = \\#_b(w) \\} \\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{ a^m b^n \\mid m, n \\geq 0 \\} \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{ w \\mid w \\in \\{ a, b \\}^*, \\#_a(w) \\equiv 2 \\ (\\text{mod}\\ 7), \\#_b(w) \\equiv 3 \\ (\\text{mod}\\ 9) \\} \\)</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460851/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-42#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following two languages over the alphabet \\(\\{a, b\\}\\):\n<br><br>\n\\(L_1 = \\{ \\alpha \\beta \\alpha \\mid \\alpha \\in \\{a, b\\}^+ \\text{ and } \\beta \\in \\{a, b\\}^+ \\}\\)<br>\n\\(L_2 = \\{ \\alpha \\beta \\alpha \\mid \\alpha \\in \\{a\\}^+ \\text{ and } \\beta \\in \\{a, b\\}^+ \\}\\)\n<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the following statements is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both \\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are regular languages.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is a regular language but \\(L_2\\) is not a regular language.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not a regular language but \\(L_2\\) is a regular language.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) is a regular language.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not a regular language but \\(L_2\\) is a regular language.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460046/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let \\( L_1 \\) be the language represented by the regular expression \\( b^* a b^*\\left(a b^* a b^*\\right)^* \\) and \\( L_2=\\left\\{w \\in(a+b)^*|| w \\mid \\leq 4\\right\\} \\), where \\( |w| \\) denotes the length of string \\( w \\). The number of strings in \\( L_2 \\) which are also in \\( L_1 \\) is ___ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "15",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422845/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-52#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(L_1, L_2 \\) be two regular languages and \\(L_3 \\) a language which is not regular. Which of the following statements is/are always TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1=L_2 \\) if and only if \\(L_1 \\cap \\overline{L_2}=\\phi \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cup L_3 \\) is not regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\overline{L_3} \\) is not regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\overline{L_1} \\cup \\overline{L_2} \\) is regular</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\overline{L_3} \\) is not regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\overline{L_1} \\cup \\overline{L_2} \\) is regular</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422829/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following two statements about regular languages:<br><br>\nS1: Every infinite regular language contains an undecidable language as a subset.<br>\nS2: Every finite language is regular.<br><br>\nWhich one of the following choices is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only S1 is true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only S2 is true</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both S1 and S2 are true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither S1 nor S2 is true</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Both S1 and S2 are true</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357504/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-36#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(L \\subseteq \\{0,1\\}^*\\) be an arbitrary regular language accepted by a minimal DFA with k states. Which one of the following languages must necessarily be accepted by a minimal DFA with k states? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L - \\{01\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L \\cup \\{01\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\( \\{0,1\\}^* -L\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L  \\cdot L\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\( \\{0,1\\}^* -L\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357531/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-9#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is true? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Every subset of a regular set is regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Every finite subset of non-regular set is regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The union of two non regular set is not regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Infinite union of finite set is regular</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Every finite subset of non-regular set is regular</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331442/isro2020-38\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following statements.<br><br>\nI.  If \\(L_1\\cup L_2\\) is regular, then both \\(L_1 \\; and \\; L_2\\) must be regular.<br>\nII. The class of regular languages is closed under infinite union.<br><br>\nWhich of the above statements is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333223/gate2020-cs-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>For \\(\\Sigma =\\{a,b\\}\\), let us consider the regular language <br>\\(L=\\{x|x=a^{2+3k} \\; or \\; x=b^{10+12k}, k\\geq 0\\}\\).<br>\nWhich one of the following can be a pumping length (the constant guaranteed by the pumping lemma) for L? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>9</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>24</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>24</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302833/gate2019-cs-15#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>If L is a regular language over \\(\\Sigma =\\{a,b\\}\\), which one of the following languages is NOT regular ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L\\cdot L^R=\\{xy|x \\in L,y^R \\in L\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{ww^R|w \\in L\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Prifix(L)={\\(x \\in \\Sigma ^*|\\exists y \\in \\Sigma ^*\\) such that \\(xy \\in L\\)}</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Suffix(L)={\\(y \\in \\Sigma ^*|\\exists x \\in \\Sigma ^*\\) such that \\(xy \\in L\\)}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{ww^R|w \\in L\\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302841/gate2019-cs-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct statement - <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(A=\\left\\{a^{n} b^{n} \\mid n=1,2,3, \\ldots\\right\\}\\)  is a regular language</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The set B, consisting of all strings made up of only \\(a^{\\prime} s\\) and \\(b^{\\prime} s\\) having equal number of \\(a^{\\prime} s\\) and bs defines a regular language</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L\\left(A^{*} B\\right) \\cap B\\) gives the set A</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213564/isro2018-24\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Language L1 is defined by the grammar: \\(S_{1}\\rightarrow aS_{1}b|\\varepsilon \\)<br>\nLanguage L2 is defined by the grammar: \\(S_{2}\\rightarrow abS_{2}|\\varepsilon\\)<br>\nConsider the following statements:<br>\nP: L1 is regular <br>\nQ: L2 is regular<br>\nWhich one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both P and Q are true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P is true and Q is false</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>P is false and Q is true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Both P and Q are false</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>P is false and Q is true</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39542/gate2016-2-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(R_{1}\\) and \\(R_{2}\\) be regular sets defined over the alphabet, then <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(R_{1} \\cap R_{2}\\)  is not regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(R_{1} \\cup R_{2}\\)  is not regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Sigma^{*}-R_{1}\\)  is regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(R_{1}^{*}\\)  is not regular</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Sigma^{*}-R_{1}\\)  is regular</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/51701/isro2015-43\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following languages is/are regular? <br> \\(L_{1}:\\{wxw^{R}|w,x \\in  \\{a,b\\}^{*} \\; and \\; |w|,|x| \\gt 0 \\}, w^{R}\\) is the reverse of string w <br>\\(L_{2}:\\{a^{n}b^{m}|m\\neq n \\; and \\; m,n\\geq 0\\}\\)<br> \\(L_{3}:\\{a^{p}b^{q}c^{r}|p,q,r\\geq 0\\}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 and L3 only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L2 only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L2 and L3 only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L3 only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 and L3 only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8254/gate2015-2-36#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(L_{1}=\\{w \\in \\{0,1\\}*|w\\) has at least as many occurrences of (110)'s as (011)'s}. <br>Let \\(L_{2}=\\{w \\in \\{0,1\\}*|w\\) has at least as many occurrence of (000)'s as (111)'s}. <br><br>Which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 is regular but not L2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L2 is regular but not L1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both L1 and L2 are regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither L1 nor L2 are regular</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 is regular but not L2</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1995/gate2014-2-36#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}